Inventory of the Jonathan Boucher Papers, 1759-1803
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Sir Frederick Morton Eden [see A/3] to Boucher
  - [Sir] Frederick Morton Eden, Ch[rist] Ch[urch], Oxford, [Eng], to Jon[athan] Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] 8 Nov. 1786, 2 pp. ALS. bears seal. (B/4/1). (Box-folder 2:21)
    He has been entertaining Mr. Zimmerman [see A/3/1] in Oxford. He agrees with Boucher on the subject of the Commercial Treaty with France and thinks that more might have been done. Problems with "Billy's Commission" by which he lost 6 months rank. Hopes to come to Epsom soon.
  - [Sir] Frederick Morton Eden, Lambeth Palace, [Eng], to [Jonathan Boucher] 18 May 1787, 2 pp. ALS. (B/4/2). (Box-folder 2:21)
    He cannot visit Boucher next week as Mrs. Moore [the Archbishop's wife, and Eden's aunt] has promised him a seat in the Prebend's Box, for the Abbey Commemoration. He hopes, however, to see Boucher at the end of the month and will be happy to be introduced to Mrs. Boucher.
  - [Sir] Frederick Morton Eden, Lambeth Palace, [Eng], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] 18 June 1787, 3 pp. ALS. (B/4/3). (Box-folder 2:21)
    He is keeping this term at the Temple. Mr. Eden [his uncle, William Eden, later Earl of Auckland] is appointed as Ambassador to Spain. Everyone is sick at Lambeth; a fever has killed a number of children.
  - [Sir] F[rederick] M[orton] Eden, Tunbridge Wells, [Eng], to [Jonathan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 29 July 1788, 3 pp. ALS. bears a seal. (B/4/4). (Box-folder 2:21)
    Tunbridge is full of old Dowagers of quality and discarded statesmen; he has dined with Lord North whose blindness has not affected his spirits. The Loyalists are still waiting for some compensation from the Government; he is less hopeful than his mother. He sends a curious inscription which he found on a gravestone in Kent.
  - [Sir] F[rederick] M[orton] E[den], to Jon[athan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] n.d. [postmark 21 July 1791], 1 p. ALS. (B/4/5). (Box-folder 2:21)
    He is unable to dine with Boucher as he has to meet some lawyers who are going on the Northern Circuit. He has heard that Burke is producing a new pamphlet next week.
  - [Sir] F[rederick] M[orton] E[den], Lincoln's Inn Fields, [England] to Jon[athan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 25 Jan. 1792, 3 pp. ALS. (B/4/6). (Box-folder 2:22)
    His mother, Lady Eden, has been in poor health; his wife [daughter of James Paul Smith] is also unwell. The Chancellor has given him a Commissionership of Bankrupt [sic].
  - [Sir] F[rederick] M[orton] Eden, No. 100 New Bond Street, [Eng.], to [Jonathan Boucher], [Eden] 12 Nov. 1792, 3 pp. ALS. (B/4/7). (Box-folder 2:22)
    He has been reading Necker [Jacques Necker, French minister and financier] but finds he takes too much for granted in his arguments. He quotes from Harrington's Oceana, written 1656, a prophetic passage about the future of France.
  - [Sir] F[rederick] M[orton] E[den], London, [Eng.], to Jon[athan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 10 May 1743, 2 pp. ALS. (B/4/8). (Box-folder 2:22)
    Boucher's partnership with Hutchinson [William Hutchinson; D.N.B.; topographer, to whose Cumberland Boucher had contributed articles] will be scarcely dissolved before, as his Prospectus announces, he begins under a new firm.
  - [Sir] F[rederick M[orton] E[den] to [Jonathan] Boucher n.d. [fragment 1797?], 1 p. ANS. (B/4/9). (Box-folder 2:22)
    He has sent Boucher a questionnaire [perhaps to gather information for his book The State of the Poor ]. He joined in praise of Boucher's sermons at a large dinner.
  - [Sir] F[rederick M[orton] E[den], Worthing, [Eng.], to [Jonathan Boucher] 27 July 1800, 1 p. ALS. (B/4/10). (Box-folder 2:22)
    (Keppell's disgrace and my little girl's birthday). He and Lady Eden will arrive at Epsom on Monday. He has read Lucien Bonaparte's speech of 14 July and finds it a most eloquent invective against Revolutions. Its purpose, Anglice, is "keep my Brother, the First Consul, as long as you can"; but he does not agree with his Eulogium on the theft of treasures from the Pope.
  - [Sir] F[rederick M[orton] E[den], W[orthing], [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Rottingdean, [Eng.] 4 Aug. 1800, 1 p. ALS. (B/4/11). (Box-folder 2:22)
    He laments over the English climate. He considered Burns a poet of great descriptive powers, pastoral humour and pathos, and regrets that he should have had such a melancholy fall. He quotes some lines from Cowper's "Retirement" about philologists. The Committee of the House of Commons has passed five or six Resolutions for the improvement of the Metropolis identical to those in Porto Bello [Eden's book on the Improvement of the Port & City of London, 1798].
- Rev. Charles Daubeny to Boucher; 1745-1827; D.N.B.; vicar of North Bradley, Dean of Salisbury; author of works upholding orthodoxy and dignity of Anglican Church.]
  - Char[le]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, at Joshua Watson's, No. 16, Mincing Lane, London, [Eng.] 7 May 1798, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/1). (Box-folder 2:23)
    He has received Boucher's valuable and interesting publication [his American sermons] from Mr. Watson [Joshua Watson; D.N.B.; wine merchant and philanthropist; married to Daubeny's niece]; he sees in this country the principles which led to the American Revolution. In an article on his Guide to the Church, the Analytical Review calls him, Boucher and Horsley [Samuel Horsley, later Bp. of St. Asaph; D.N.B.] the Lauds of the present day. He sent Mr. Wilberforce a copy of his book but does not know whether he will read it.
  - le]s Daubeny, N[orth] Bradley, near Trowbridge, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 20 June 1798, 3 pp. ALS. (B/5/2). (Box-folder 2:23)
    He asks Boucher how to direct a letter to the Rt. Rev. W.A. Drummond at Hawthorndon [William Abernethy Drummond, Bp. of Edinburgh]; the Bishop believes his Guide to the Church may do some good in Scotland and wishes to have it abridged there. Daubeny would like Boucher's opinion of Sir Richard Hill's "farrago" as he intends to answer it [Sir Richard Hill; D.N.B.; supporter of Calvinistic Methodism, attacked Daubeny's Guide, and carried on a long controversy with him by pamphlets]. The work of churchmen is usually to go over old ground.
  - Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Mr. [Jonathan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 28 Dec[embe]r 1798, 3 pp. ALS. (B/5/3). (Box-folder 2:23)
    He apologizes for not acknowledging earlier sermons Boucher sent him, but he has been much occupied with his new church at Bath [Christ Church, Walcot] and with his reply to Sir Richard Hill, which Boucher advised him to write; he would like him to read the first part of this work; Mr. William Stevens has written to tell him that Mr. Jones [of Nayland] is thinking of replying to Sir Richard. He asks whether Boucher has heard from his friend, the Scotch Bishop [of Edinburgh], how the abridgement of the Guide to the Church is progressing.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to [Jonathan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 8 Jan[uar]y 1799, 3 pp. ALS. (B/5/4). (Box-folder 2:23)
    He is sending part of his reply to Sir Richard Hill for Boucher to read and criticize.
  - [rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to [Jonathan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 18 Feb. 1799, 3 pp. ALS. (B/5/5). (Box-folder 2:23)
    He has received his packet of papers and Boucher's notes upon them and is sending him another packet which he should keep until the remaining part of the publication comes before him; he would like Boucher's opinion on the scope of the work, particularly on the subjects of Calvinism, Church Unity and Schism.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to [Jonathan] Boucher 22 Feb[ruar]y 1799, 3 pp. ALS. (B/5/6). (Box-folder 2:23)
    He is sending Boucher the final part of his work which has already been corrected by Mr. Bowdler, [John Bowdler, D.N.B.]; although he wishes everything harsh-sounding to be cut out of the work, he thinks that Bowdler has carried this a little too far, and would welcome Boucher's opinion on those corrections; Boucher can expect no other reward than the satisfaction of supporting the Cause of the Church.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, No. 8 Cresent, Bath, [Eng.], to [Jonathan Boucher 18 Mar[ch] 1799, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/7a). (Box-folder 2:23)
    The first part of his work is in the press, and he asks Boucher to return any part of the remainder with which he has finished. He asks if Boucher has seen Bp. Drummond's abridgment of the Guide; and abridgement of the work, with addenda from the letters to Sir Richard Hill, would be a useful book for general circulation; he is unwilling to undertake this task himself as an author is the worst qualified to abridge his own work. The liberal ideas and smooth sentences of such modern speculatists as Dr. Paley [William Paley, D.N.B.] may be preferred to his old-fashioned writing as more accommodating. He sent a copy of the Guide to the Archbishop of Canterbury but he did not acknowledge it.
  - Suggested title page for Daubeny's Letters to Sir Richard Hill [which were published under the title An Appendix to the Guide to the Church] n.d., Wrapper of (B/5/7a). 1 p. AMS. (B/5/7b). (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to [Jonathan] Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 10 April 1799, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/8). (Box-folder 2:24)
    He is revising the last part of his work, incorporating many of Boucher's suggestions; he hopes it may be better received than the Guide which had a very poor review in the British Critic; his friend, the author of Reform or Ruin, [John Bowdler], does not wish to undertake a review; Daubeny considers Boucher the fittest person to do this. He commends the sound constitutional principles of the Anti-Jacobin; his abilities are at the service of the editor [John Gifford, D.N.B.]; he considers "that schismatic courier", The Gospel Magazine, a danger to the Constitution.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, N. Bradley, Trowbridge, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.]. 16 July 1799, 2 pp. ALS. (B/5/9). (Box-folder 2:24)
    He has directed Hatchard [John Hatchard, D.N.B., publisher] to keep six copies of the book for Boucher to distribute to his friends at Shrewsbury, Bp. Skinner [of Aberdeen] and his father, and the Rev. Dr. Glegg [sic: George Gleig, D.N.B., later Bp. of Brechin]. He hopes his book has aided the cause of the church. Thanks Boucher for his revisions.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, N[orth] Bradley, [Trowbridge], [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 24 Sept[embe]r 1799, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/10). (Box-folder 2:24)
    He has received strong and decided letters from Bp. Skinner and Dr. Gleig, and believes that will write good reviews of his book; however, he is sorry that Boucher would not undertake this task. He is sorry to hear that the Anti-Jacobin is declining and wishes he had more leisure to write for it. He has written a pamphlet to Mrs. Hannah More, whose faith, like that of Mr. Wilberforce, is Calvinism in disguise; her doctrine that Faith is necessarily productive of works is a most dangerous error, a true Child of Enthusiasm. An explanation of his reasoning on that point.
  - Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.]. 23 Oct[obe]r 1799, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/11). (Box-folder 2:24)
    Sir Richard Hill is to reply to Daubeny's answer; all Calvinists are the spawn of the Scotch Covenanters and, were it in their power, would be just as intolerant; Daubeny has also been attacked by a brother clergyman. Of some parts of Mrs. More's writings he has as high an opinion as Boucher, but as she has it in her power to do so much good, he wishes her to be "wholly with us"; however, the difference is in expression rather than idea. He will use his influence at Winchester College [where he was a Fellow] on behalf of Boucher's son, but application for admission should be made immediately; he will find out about fees when his own boys come home for Christmas.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to [Jonathan Boucher] 7 Jan[uary] 1800, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/12). (Box-folder 2:24)
    The fees of Winchester College have nearly doubled since his time, being £60 p.a. He has met Dr. Matthew Spens who told him that Bp. Drummond has lost a colleague [the principal Minister of the English Episcopal Chapel in Edinburgh] and, wishing him to be replaced by a minister of the Church of England has written to Boucher [see also A/4a-b]; however, Bp. Watson Richard Watson, Bp. of Llandaff, D.N.B.] has written someone else a testimonial, which Daubeny considers a very poor recommendation. He and Bp. Douglas [see A/4] agree that the Anti-Jacobin is in need of assistance. He disapproves of Bp. Porteaus' [of London] support of Hannah More; the Bishop has acted very badly in another matter which Daubeny cannot explain in a letter.
  - Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] [28 January 1800], 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/13). (Box-folder 2:24)
    He is sorry that the fees at Winchester have risen so high, and fears that this trend will lead to less learning in the Church. His Letters to Mrs. Hannah More have received very handsome reviews, but his critic, Sir Richard Hill, has appeared again and attacked both the Guide and the Appendix; Daubeny is not eager to write another reply.
  - Charles Daubeny to [Jonathan Boucher] 27 Feb[ruar]y 1800, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/14). (Box-folder 2:25)
    He has read through Boucher's papers and returns them with his comments. The tenet that Faith is necessarily productive is very near the Calvinistic doctrine of the irresistibility of divine Grace; as long as Mrs. More continues to frequent independent chapels he will doubt her attachment to the Church of England; he gives her credit for much good done on the best principle, but not for the best judgment or the best information. When he has time, he will tell Boucher more about the Bp. of London, whom he thinks neither sound nor honest.
  - Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] 16 April 1800, 4 pp. ALS. bears seal. (B/5/15). (Box-folder 2:25)
    He has sent Boucher his comments on Sir Richard Hill's last publication; he believes he should be answered as in these times, his work may do mischief. He is also sending a sermon by a Mr. Dennis in defence of Mrs. More, who keeps a sort of school for the younger, self-confident, "hop, step and jump" clergy; he has reviewed it at length as it misrepresents what he wrote in his Letters to Mrs. Hannah More. He has received a letter from a Mr. Ludlam [possibly Thomas Ludlam, D.N.B., theologian and opponent of Calvinism] complimenting him on this work.
  - Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 7 Nov[embe]r 1800, 7 pp. ALS. (B/5/16). (Box-folder 2:25)
    He believes his packet containing Mr. Dennis's sermon may not have reached Boucher; Dennis is one of those self-sufficient, forward young Divines now growing up in the Church. He has seen Boucher's handsome review of a work by the Bp. of Lincoln but doubts whether the Bishop is as orthodox and apostolical as he is represented to be.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] [14 January 1801], 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/17). (Box-folder 2:25)
    Bp. Skinner [of Aberdeen] has asked him to reply to Dr. Campbell's posthumous publication [Lectures on Ecclesiastical History] by Dr. George Campbell]; he feels that this might seem like presumption in a Church of England clergyman, and that Bp. Skinner himself is the fittest person to defend the Scottish Episcopacy. The Anti-Jacobin has reviewed a work by Mr. Evans, who was Daubeny's curate until dismissed with disgrace.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, [Bath, Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 21 January 1801, 2 pp. ALS. (B/5/18). (Box-folder 2:25)
    He encloses a letter he has written at the pressing solicitation of Bp. Drummond to Lord Kinnoul who was a friend of his at Oxford; the Earl has already consulted the Archbishop of Canterbury on the subject [of the Scottish Church]. Daubeny has heard once more from Mr. Jones Dennis who has sent him notice of the Churchman's Magazine which is shortly to be published.
  - Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to [Lord Kinnoul, Robert Auriol Hay-Drummond, 1751-1804, Earl of Kinnoull] November 1800, 8 pp. ACyS. (B/5/19). (Box-folder 2:25)
    The Bishop is the center of Unity in his diocese and any departure from the obligation of ecclesiastical Unity is schism; English Bishops have no authority is Scotland so the claim of the clergy of the Anglican communions in Scotland to be attached to the Church of England is without foundation; they owe canonical obedience to the Scottish Bishops and any resistance is resistance to the Ordinance of God.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, [Bath, Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] 3 March 1801, 4 pp. ALS. bears seal of Daubeny. (B/5/20). (Box-folder 2:26)
    He is sending Boucher some of his sermons intended to publication as a relaxation from etymological research. The British Critic, which he had thought at least Episcopalian, is doing more harm than good to the cause of the Scottish Episcopacy. The Anti-Jacobin Review exaggerates the value of Dr. Randolph's sermons.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 6 May 1801, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/21). (Box-folder 2:26)
    He has heard nothing from Boucher about the papers he sent him but his nephew [Joshua] Watson says he is very busy and very lazy. A new medical publication by a Dr. Haggarth is said to have been read before the library & Philosophical Society at Bath; such literary juntas, full of half- informed, unprincipled men, are all the fashion; this society, self-constituted at Bath, is headed by infidels and Quakers; the Treasurer is Matthews, the Quaker; Dr. Gibbes [Sir George Smith Gibbes, D.N.B.] is the secretary; Sir George Colebrooke, the President; and Sir William Watson [D.N.B.], the Vice President.
  - Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 29 May 1801, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/22). (Box-folder 2:26)
    He is sending Boucher some further Discourses with a Preface addressed to the younger clergy mentioning Dr. Campbell's work, as Bp. Skinner suggested. Dr. Randolph merely skimmed over a great subject; the admiration of William Stevens ("not my friend") for him is a species of self- idolatry. If Bp. Skinner wishes to see Daubeny's letter to Lord Kinnoul, will Boucher send on his copy [B/5/19]; criticism of Dr. Campbell's book. He knows nothing of Mr. Faber, but as he is a Calvinist, their works will hardly cover the same ground.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, N[orth] Bradley, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] [16 September 1801], 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/23). (Box-folder 2:26)
    He is sending via Joshua Watson, a very handsome letter he received from John Bowden, D.D., Principal of the Episcopal Academy in Connecticut; he is much impressed by the sound principles and seal of both the American and the Scottish Episcopacy. He asks Boucher to help him make his Discourses fit for the press; the lengthy criticism of Dr. Campbell's works needs a more formal introduction.
  - John Bowden, Cheshire, Connecticut, to Charles Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.] 18 June 1801, Cp. of ALS. (B/5/24). (Box-folder 2:26)
    On behalf of the Convocation of the Episcopal Church in Connecticut he thanks Daubeny for Writing his Guide to the Church. He sent for a copy on reading a review in the Anti-Jacobin, and was so impressed by it that he and his colleagues are determined that it shall be a standard book for candidates for Holy Orders. Expresses admiration and affection for England and its institutions.
  - C[harles] D[aubeny], Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 19 Nov[embe]r 1801, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/25). (Box-folder 2:27)
    His Discourses have been much improved by Boucher's revisions. He has just been sent a pamphlet by a layman attacking him as a traducer of Baxter; "the Laity write with so much confidence on divine Subjects, that if we are to take their own word for it, the Clergy may shut up shop"; he believes that he gave Baxter as much credit as he deserved in his Guide to the Church, in fact, he treated him generously. Lists misdeeds [in Daubeny's eyes] of [Richard] Baxter.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 19 Mar[ch] 1802, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/26). (Box-folder 2:27)
    He is sending copies of his Discourses [published under the title of Eight Discourses on the Connexion between the Old and New Testament ] to Boucher and Bps. Drummond and Skinner; he hopes that Boucher and Skinner will review it. He hoped that Bp. Skinner would have been able to visit Bath to see his church [Christ Church, Walcot] there. He has received Boucher's Prospectus [of his Glossary of Archaic and Provincial Words ] and has put his own name down and that of Winchester College Library.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, Bath, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 27 March 1802, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/27). (Box-folder 2:27)
    He has asked Dr. Gleig to review his Discourses as Boucher has declined to do so. He believes William Stevens to be fundamentally an honest man, but his passions so run away with his judgment, that he is subject to be imposed upon by those who are not honest men. Daubeny defends Public Seminaries on a general principle, considering them to be the best security against Ignorance and Enthusiasm.
  - Cha[rle]s Daubeny, North Bradley, Trowbridge, [Eng.], to Jonathan Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 11 July 1803, 4 pp. ALS. (B/5/28). (Box-folder 2:27)
    He hopes that Boucher will read through the Guide to the Church making marginal remarks, preparatory to a new edition. He refers to the prospect of a stall at Durham for Boucher. Exhorts Boucher to spend his time in defense of the church.
  - W[illia]m Cobbett, Philadelphia, [Pa.], to Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, Surrey, [Eng.] 24 Aug[ust] 1798, 2 pp. ALS. (Box-folder 2:28)
    Thanks for JB's book; attitudes to the American Revolution; no possibility of an edition of JB's work selling in America; WC's attachment to England.